Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/derricklj (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Research and Development (R&D)
Product Innovation
Resiliency

Publications

Entreprenuers Grow Business

Molding Youth Into Entreprenuers

Derrick L. Johnson

Encounter Al CEO | Morgan Stanley, Hearst & SRI Backed | Ex-Accenture & Roku | Mentor | Dad Joke Expert

San Francisco Bay Area

Summary

Derrick is an early-stage venture founder, tech investor, AI and robotics enthusiast, and experienced mentor, speaker, and board member. He has brought complex products from concept to reality for iconic brands such as Roku, Disney, and Accenture. A self-described "collaborative maverick", he knows how to succeed in difficult environments.

Experience

Encounter Al Founder November 2022 - Present (1 year 10 months) San Francisco Bay Area

We improve drive-thru operations with our conversational AI. Customers enjoy human-like interactions that allow for easy ordering and on-the-fly customization. Plus Encounter AI is more accurate than any other available solution, so customers get the right order and they get it faster. For a simple monthly fee, we bring smart tech to fast food.

Led the incubation and launch of a groundbreaking Al-powered product, targeting enterprise-level marketing solutions, focused on revolutionizing conversational commerce experiences.

Assembled and directed a highly skilled team of Engineers, Prototypers, Designers, and Researchers, driving the product from concept to launch.

Developed and executed a comprehensive product strategy, including market research, competitive analysis, user interviews, and a go-to-market plan for initial customer acquisition.

Established and managed a product roadmap, prioritizing features based on user needs, business impact, and technical feasibility.

Collaborated with board to support incubation efforts, ensuring strategic alignment and resource availability.

Responsible for the product's Profit & Loss, managing budgets to align with product goals and financial objectives.

Defined and monitored key performance metrics, leveraging data to guide strategic decisions and identify new product opportunities.

Roku Inc.

Sr. Software Engineer (Voice AI, Data, Analytics) October 2019 - November 2022 (3 years 2 months) San Jose, California, United States

Role Intersection: ML Ops, Generative AI, TV Commerce (Hackathon), Data Analytics

On Deck Fellowship (ODF 4) June 2020 - July 2020 (2 months)

Encounter Al

Founder

October 2018 - October 2019 (1 year 1 month)

Lead 'Human Like' agent research and development of in terms of accuracy, insights, and responsiveness, in response to shifting labor market demands.

SAP Concur

Senior Data Architect

December 2017 - October 2018 (11 months)

San Francisco Bay Area

Lead data engineering platform migration efforts to support operational marketing, traveler reporting, personalization, and product monetization.

Distributed Systems: MySQL, HDFS (Hive), Kafka

Languages: Python, Java

Accenture

2 years 10 months

Growth and Strategy - Tech Labs September 2015 - December 2017 (2 years 4 months)

Greater Chicago Area

Provided strategic innovation, market research and thought leadership to identify and deploy long-term growth opportunities covering all segments of Accenture Operations included (e.g. F&A, Software Entitlements, Future Workforce, Digital Outsourcing, etc.)

Partnered to effectively influence and lead cross-functional stakeholders through technical exploration and solutions to business problems.

Delivered strategic insights and business policy recommendations to our Global Operating Committee leadership based on financial modeling, benchmarking research, and product strategy while managing competing priorities and deadlines.

Participated in pre-sales customer visits to understand, develop, propose, deliver and lead innovation offerings and engagements.

Solutions:

Operations (RPA / AI, Human + Machine) Hospitality (Conversational AI) Travel (Predictive Analytics)

Data & Analytics - Associate Manager March 2015 - September 2015 (7 months) Greater Chicago Area

Developed enhanced forecasting and price planning infrastructure and recommendation systems for a top tier Entertainment and Tourism Diamond Client.

Distributed Systems: Kafka, HDFS (Hive), MySQL

Visualization: Proprietary

Data Providers: Nielsen, Experian, Federal Reserve

Language: Python, SQL

Adelman Travel Group **Analytics Engineering Lead** June 2011 - February 2015 (3 years 9 months) Greater Milwaukee Area

Managed a business intelligence initiative to enhance traveler tracking and budgetary forecasting across \$600M+ in annual travel spend.

Delivered a market differentiated solution across multiple suppliers that enabled Adelman to manage the complete trip cost and report on items beyond air, car and hotel to include meals, mileage, entertainment and other expense data.

Drove innovation initiatives, product governance, deliverables planning and design of entirely new Adelman product features to deliver against team and company goals.

Distributed Systems: SQL Server

Visualization: Cognos

Data Providers: Sabre, TravelPort, SAP

Language: .NET, SQL

WageWorks
Data Integration Engineer
July 2006 - June 2011 (5 years)
Greater Milwaukee Area

Developed and integrated disparate systems to ensure accurate and robust data was available to our clients and third party transit e-commerce systems.

Delivered a mobile application prototype to drive market differentiation.

Education

Marquette University
Bachelor of Arts (B.A.), Management Information Systems,
General · (2011 - 2016)

YCombinator Startup School Startup Principles, Fundraising · (2018 - 2018)